Here's how you can advocate for yourself if your doctor doesn't take your concerns seriously.
I'm a fourth year medical student and one of the first things we learned in medical school is how
to put together a differential diagnosis. It basically means tell me all the other things
that it could be. For example, maybe you have a headache or you're feeling lightheaded or have
chest pain, abdominal pain, or you just feel really sad and you bring this up to your doctor or
clinician and they just blow it off. Oh, it's probably nothing. I want you to ask them,
what is your differential diagnosis for this chest pain, for this abdominal pain, for my
lightheadedness? This is where you catch them off guard because they weren't expecting you to know
that word. So then they'll have to list it out. Well, your chest pain, I mean, it could be nothing
or it could be a myocardial infarction. It could be a pulmonary embolism. It could be an aortic
dissection. It could be blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. So next you ask them, how have you ruled those
other ones out? Now they got to explain things to you even better. Ask them, what's the evidence
for and against that differential? Well, I guess it could be a heart attack because, you know,
you're having the chest pain, the pressure, you know, it's worse. The shortness of breath is worse
with activity and, you know, the classic signs. How have I ruled that out? That's a good question.
Maybe I should get that EKG.